<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The second part of Babel's-builders unmask't in an answer to a false charge against W.R. and T.C. in a book entituled, John Penington's complaint, &amp;c.</title>
            <title>Babel's-builders unmask't. Part 2</title>
            <author>Crisp, Thomas, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35011</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6953</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10391</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12534106</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12534106</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62826</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35011)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62826)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 311:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The second part of Babel's-builders unmask't in an answer to a false charge against W.R. and T.C. in a book entituled, John Penington's complaint, &amp;c.</title>
                  <title>Babel's-builders unmask't. Part 2</title>
                  <author>Crisp, Thomas, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed: Tho. Crisp.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Penington, John, 1655-1710. --  Complaint against William Rogers.</term>
               <term>Rogers, William, d. ca. 1709.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-03</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:62826:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE SECOND PART OF Babel's-Builders <hi>Vnmask't,</hi> In an ANSWER to a Falſe Charge againſt <hi>W. R.</hi> and <hi>T. C.</hi> in a Book Entituled, <hi>John Penington's Complaint,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>IN the ſaid Complaint againſt <hi>W. R.</hi> put out in the name of <hi>J. Pening<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> I find the Scripture fulfilled in the Approvers thereof as well as in <hi>J. P. That the time would come, they will not indure Sound Doctrine.</hi> For although that <hi>Teſtimony</hi> cited from <hi>Jſ. P's</hi> (was Sound Truth) who was one of the moſt experienced among them; yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it thwarts their preſent Deſigns and Intereſt, therefore they revile the Publiſhers and the Owners thereof, as appears by the black Names and Characters to <hi>W. R.</hi> and <hi>T. C. Notoriouſly guilty of premeditated Falſhood, impious Prevaricators, Betrayers of Truth, and the ſincere Profeſſors thereof unto the wicked; unworthy, and untrue to his word, a Shame to Moral Heathens, hardened Heart, proſtrate Soul, in ſtiffneſs againſt the Lord; departed from the juſt Principle in themſelves, and dayly doing deſpite to the Spirit of Grace, looſe libertine,</hi> &amp;c. after all their other kindneſſes in the lower end of the <hi>9th.</hi> pag. by craft (which they be well skil'd in) term <hi>W. Rogers Forger,</hi> whereby their Book ſeems more like a <hi>Popiſh Bull</hi> than a <hi>Complaint.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the great and black Crimes pretended againſt <hi>T. C.</hi> is becauſe, <hi>He publiſhed ſome Teſtimonies of</hi> Iſaac Peningtons, <hi>and ſaw not his Book, but publiſhed them on the ſole Authority of</hi> W. R. whom you term <hi>a Proſeſſed Adverſary,</hi> pag. 8. but yet (although the young Man hath too much Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence) he dares not ſay, It was not his Fathers: but I do now (as afore) affirm it was every word (that I publiſhed as <hi>Iſaac Peningtons</hi>) really his, without any additions or alteration of the ſenſe of the words, only abridged, and advice thereof given in the <hi>Preface,</hi> and alſo in pag. 11. &amp; recommended
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62826:2"/> to the Book. But whereas <hi>J. P.</hi> ſaith, that I publiſhed it ſolely on the credit of <hi>W. R. That is falſe,</hi> and he, and his Approvers <hi>Slanderers</hi> and <hi>Falſe-Accuſers;</hi> for I had other ſatisfaction from them whoſe Honeſty, Ability and Credit exceeds <hi>J. P</hi>'s although I did tranſcribe it from <hi>W. R</hi>s. being then from <hi>London,</hi> where I had not the opportunity of <hi>Iſaac Pening<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> Book, and being not willing to exceed two Sheets, therefore did abridge ſome Sentences, but not to the alteration thereof. But if I had only taken <hi>W. R</hi>'s Authority therein; it is well known, that he is a Man whoſe Credit will paſs for a greater Concernment with many honeſt Friends, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding your Abuſes and Slanders of him, becauſe he hath detected your <hi>Apoſtacy.</hi> And ſeeing ye have not, nor cannot prove <hi>W. R</hi>'s Citation, nor mine falſe; but <hi>W. R.</hi> hath in the <hi>Sixth Part</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian-Quaker</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted that he took all his (<hi>viz.</hi> 10 pages) all together, and not left out, altered, or added any words: therefore it is the ſame as if I had tranſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed them from <hi>Iſaac Penningtons,</hi> as I have done the <hi>Second Edition</hi> before Publication: and yet you are as much offended with that, (and indeed have as much cauſe) for the words be the ſame, and will ſtand a Witneſs againſt <hi>Your Idol,</hi> G. F<hi>'s Laws,</hi> although he have many ſuch as <hi>Solomon Eccles</hi> and <hi>C. Taylor</hi> to adore them as from the <hi>Oracles of Divine Breath</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Pennington</hi> at the lower end of his firſt page, cites <hi>W. R</hi>'s words or preamble (that he mentions juſt before the Teſtimony) and in ſecond page, ſays, <hi>Who would deſire fairer dealing:</hi> and notwithſtanding all your black and bitter revilings of <hi>W. R.</hi> afore mentioned, have not proved that <hi>W. R.</hi> hath not performed what he there ſaid: and if <hi>W. R.</hi> had cited but as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny lines as he hath done pages of <hi>Iſaac Penningtons,</hi> and taken intire Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences that depend not on others, he had not wronged him, nor abuſed the Reader. For <hi>W. R.</hi> never ſaid it was the beginning, or end of <hi>Iſaac Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningtons,</hi> nor the whole, but on the contrary, ſaid it was a Part; therefore <hi>W. R.</hi> not baſe nor untrue to his word, but you falſe Accuſers. For in pag. 78. of <hi>Examination, Iſ. P.</hi> ſayeth (ſpeaking of Chriſt) <hi>He waited until that was opened in his Diſciples which was able to receive his Teſtimony, and he made uſe of his Power of Life,</hi> &amp;c. — <hi>To inable him — to ſerve and wait in patience for the fulfilling the Will of the Father.</hi> Theſe Lines need not the whole to explain them, and do prove what <hi>W. R.</hi> affirms, and againſt what he oppoſes, and he is not ſuch a crafty <hi>Mangler</hi> as you term him, (nor hath he acted as you have in your <hi>Hypocriſy,</hi> &amp;c. publiſhed in the name of <hi>T. L.</hi> alſo the <hi>Accuſer,</hi> &amp;c.) For there be many more Sentences in that Part which he omitted, that be againſt your Impoſitions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for that you charge <hi>W. R.</hi> for <hi>mangling,</hi> and <hi>T. C.</hi> for <hi>curtaling,</hi> yet obſerve but your own Doings; you eite a few words of the Epiſtle to <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth: The Spirit of the Prophets is ſubject to the Prophets.</hi> Now you would think it harſh Judgment to be treated with ſuch Language (as you do <hi>W. R.</hi>)
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:62826:2"/> becauſe you have not quoted the whole Chapter, or at leaſt, the words next adjoyning: and by your own Meaſures, you may juſtly be termed <hi>Manglers</hi> and <hi>Curtalers</hi> of Scripture, and deſerve thoſe Names given <hi>W. R.</hi> and <hi>T. C.</hi> too many, and too foul to repeat. And that which aggravates your Confidence and Unrighteouſneſs in ſo reviling <hi>W. R.</hi> for not citing all, or more of <hi>Iſaac Penningtons</hi> Teſtimony, is in your <hi>6th.</hi>p. ſay that he hath cited words to the ſame effect, as thoſe he left out: whereby it appears it would but have been needleſs Repitition of him to have cited the ſame again. And thoſe by him cited, are ſuch plain Truths, and according to Scripture, that they need not others to explain them. Pag. 5. you ſay, W. R. <hi>would make appear that</hi> Iſaac Pennington <hi>was againſt any Outward Form of Government, Order, and Diſcipline;</hi> but <hi>W. R.</hi> doth not ſay ſo, nor any ill, or diſreſpective word of <hi>Iſaac Penington</hi> in all his Book, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in that alſo you be <hi>falſe Accuſers.</hi> And for that Sentence which <hi>J. P.</hi> ſaith in his <hi>4th.</hi> pag. <hi>W. R.</hi> left out, becauſe <hi>it pinched him,</hi> (it was not in ſo far as he cited) the words be theſe. <hi>And the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity being thus kept, all will come into one outwardly, alſo at length, as the Light grows in every one,</hi> — <hi>but this muſt be patiently waited for from the Hand of God, who hath the right way of effecting it,</hi>— <hi>and not harſhly</hi> — <hi>attempted by the rough hand of Man.</hi> Theſe <hi>J.P.</hi> truly cites, but when he comes to infer from them, then he is guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of what he falſly charges <hi>W. R.</hi> with: For he is ſo much in haſt for <hi>Outward Oneneſs</hi> with G. F'<hi>s Laws,</hi> that he takes no notice of the explaining words, but leaps over them; he forgets to ſtay for <hi>Outward Oneneſs</hi> until the Lord Effect it, as his Father ſaid; to plead but to ſtay until the Grace of God <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the Conſcience,</hi> is now termed, <hi>a looſe Plea, and the Root of Ranteriſm</hi> with ſome of <hi>G. F</hi>'s chief Men of War: for they muſt <hi>Eſtabliſh the Church in the Holy Order of the Goſpel</hi> (as they call it) And this their haſty impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <hi>G. F</hi>'s Laws, is the great cauſe of difference. For <hi>W. R.</hi> &amp;c. do not oppoſe any <hi>Outward Oneneſs</hi> that Friends are by the Lords Hand brought into, but incourages it. And <hi>Iſ . P</hi>'s words allowed their plain and true meaning, are not pinſhing to <hi>W. R.</hi> for <hi>Iſ. P.</hi> ſaith, <hi>And the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity being thus kept,</hi> &amp;c. which relates to ſomething afore mentioned: where he ſayth, <hi>He that hath a Taſt of the one Heart, and one Way, knoweth that no variety of Practices, which is of God, can make a Breach in the true <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, &amp;c. — And every one keeping here, there is one Heart kept in the midſt of all variety and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of Practiſes.</hi> Whereby it is clear, that the Unity he believed, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted of diverſity of Practiſes. Which is the ſame with <hi>W. R.</hi> &amp;c. and is that <hi>J. P.</hi> and his Adherents are ſo againſt, <hi>viz. Bearing with, and not judging one another, as Iſaac Pennington</hi> ſays (truly) <hi>is likelier meanes to bring into One Outwardly, than compelling.</hi> And <hi>J. P.</hi> doth falſly and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſly ſay (in his 5th.pag.) <hi>W.R.</hi> durſt not truſt his <hi>Reader</hi> with thoſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62826:3"/> words; <hi>For if it be ſo, that all arc to be of one Mind or Practice Outwardly, yet that doth not prove that all muſt come to Conformity to</hi> G. F.'<hi>s Laws.</hi> But it may as well be inferred from thoſe words, that <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. will come into one with <hi>J. P's</hi> Father, according to his many Teſtimonies, <hi>viz. Not to ſtrive to force into one Mind, but walk ſweetly together in Love, although in diverſity of Practices;</hi> which is alſo according to Scripture, and the antient Teſtimony, and Chriſts Rule; <hi>Do as you would be done by;</hi> therefore more properly to be expected and pleaded for from this very <hi>pinching Sentence,</hi> as <hi>J. P.</hi> calls it, than to plead for Impoſitions.</p>
            <p>And for that <hi>J. P.</hi> would reflect on <hi>W. R.</hi> in pag. 7.8. for uſing the words <hi>We,</hi> and <hi>Our,</hi> only as a flouriſh: it is well known, that abler and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſter than <hi>J. P.</hi> have, and will own themſelves concern'd. However <hi>W. R.</hi> needs no help againſt ſuch as <hi>J. P.</hi> but his own work of <hi>Falſhood</hi> is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient correction to himſelf; who notwithſtanding he hath not proved any wrong done by <hi>W. R.</hi> but that he hath performed what he ſaid, and that <hi>J. P.</hi> ſays, <hi>is fair Dealing;</hi> yet after all his other foul Language, doth in the 9th. pag. no leſs than term <hi>W. R, a Forger:</hi> but it appears, that the cauſe of all their rage againſt him, is, becauſe he hath endeavoured to prove <hi>G. F.</hi> but a fallable man, unto whom <hi>Chriſtopher Taylor</hi> and <hi>Solomon Eccles</hi> &amp;c. have given unſitting Titles and Names.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as <hi>J. P.</hi> hath not made good his charge of wrong done by <hi>W. R.</hi> to his Father in his Citations, nor diſproved any words that <hi>W. R.</hi> or <hi>T. C.</hi> cited as his Fathers, but that they are really ſo, nor any thing omitted by <hi>W. R.</hi> that was in the Part he cited. Therefore it can be no Injury to <hi>Iſaac Penington,</hi> or the <hi>Reader,</hi> that <hi>T. C.</hi> tranſcribed that Part of <hi>Iſaac Peningtons</hi> Teſtimony from <hi>W. R</hi>'s Book, which was occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned as afore.</p>
            <p>And for that <hi>J. P.</hi> in pag. 8. reflects on <hi>T. C.</hi> that he did not <hi>Berean-like</hi> ſearch his Fathers Writings. Thoſe Teſtimonies by <hi>T. C.</hi> are ſo agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Truth and Scriptures, that if <hi>J. P.</hi> and a hundred more of <hi>G. F</hi>'s <hi>Men of War</hi> do deny, or oppoſe them, yet <hi>T. C.</hi> would not be aſhamed to own them. And they were not publiſhed as a Charge or Defamation to <hi>Iſ. P.</hi> but will ſtand on Record to his Praiſe. And if any Injury be to <hi>Iſ. P.</hi> it is by him, and his Adherents that would inſinuate that his Father intended any other way than his words are, and would make him contradict himſelf and Truth alſo. And for that <hi>J. P.</hi> ſaith, <hi>T. C. added wide Inferences of his own, as of a Liberty in paying Tithes, as a civil Right:</hi> Indeed he ſayeth true in that he ſaith, <hi>wide Inferences,</hi> for that Paſſage he is ſo offended at, is about ſeven pages wide from his Fathers, and two other Friends Teſtimonies between: but if <hi>J. P.</hi> think that I ſhould ask him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> licence to mention his Fathers Name, or Writings, he is miſtaken.</p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>J. P.</hi> ſaith, <hi>far from his Fathers Senſe and Practice,</hi> I did not ſay
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62826:3"/> it was his Fathers Senſe or Practice, but his Father doth ſay, pag, 64. <hi>Chriſt is ſole Lord and Judge of the Conſcience,</hi> Rom. 14.4. <hi>and not either Miniſter or Church,</hi>—<hi>that is many times required to be left upon a further degree of Knowledge given, which was not required to be left before,</hi> &amp;c. This proves what <hi>T. C.</hi> affirms, That we ought not to judge one another about Matters that relate to Conſcience.</p>
            <p>As for that cited as <hi>E. B</hi>'s Viſion, It hath been ſo received and deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from, and to many Eminent Friends. <hi>T.C.</hi> doth not pretend that he ſaw him write it, but if any miſtake were in the aſſigned Author, the truth is no leſs truth.</p>
            <p>And whereas <hi>J. P.</hi> faith, <hi>T. C</hi>'s Title is <hi>fallacious:</hi> had any thing been ſet in the Title which was not in the Book, then he might have ſo ſaid, nor do I underſtand it is deceit, not to expreſs all on the Title, that is in the Book. But to me there appears greater deceit in the Concluſion of his, where he faith, <hi>Let this be diſperſed only where</hi> W. R's <hi>abuſive Book hath gone,</hi> (which Caution pretends privacy) Yet this Book was ſold to Strangers, that had no appearance like <hi>Quakers,</hi> and lay publick on the <hi>Bookſellers</hi> Boards to the view of any, and ſold to them that never ſaw <hi>W. R</hi>'s Book.</p>
            <p>And for that' <hi>J. P.</hi> in pag. 8. about <hi>Tithes,</hi> ſayth, <hi>It is a denying Chriſt come in the Fleſh;</hi> it needs his further Explanation, eſpecially ſince we find that many of the <hi>Believing Jews</hi> were found in the Practice of <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion</hi> (equally abrogated with <hi>Tithes</hi>) and not Judged for ſuch their Practice, whil'ſt through Faith they were not led from under it. <hi>T. C.</hi> doth not plead for <hi>Tithes,</hi> but believes them to be an oppreſſion, <hi>But that every one that pays them, denyes Chriſt being come in the Fleſh,</hi> I think, is too raſh; when the payment thereof is grounded on a Submiſſion to the Eſtabliſhed Laws, and not on a Religious Score, in purſuance of the Law under the <hi>Firſt Covenant</hi> abrogated by Chriſt. For the <hi>Tribute</hi> demanded of Chriſt, was contrary to their Law, yet he paid it. Alſo to be <hi>ſmitten,</hi> or <hi>compelled to go a Mile,</hi> But yet Chriſt commanded to bear it, and do them; and for all <hi>J. P.</hi> &amp;c. are ſo angry, I will adventure to add without their licence, that I believe they that pay them only out of <hi>Chriſtian Submiſſion</hi> to the Magiſtrate, do bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than thoſe that deny them, only becauſe <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. do ſo order, or will Judge them therefore.</p>
            <p>And for the uſing of <hi>plain Language,</hi> or any Practice Friends uſe, or refuſe, as in Conſcience to God, <hi>T. C.</hi> condemns not, only <hi>Imitation.</hi> And for that <hi>J. P.</hi> ſaith is a <hi>Lye,</hi> if he mean ſaying <hi>you</hi> to a ſingle Perſon, this I think is too uncharitable &amp; a rude word in it ſelf, and ſo accounted by <hi>J.P.</hi> as in his 14th. p. 1. 10. he ſays <hi>W. R. foul-mouthedly gives</hi> G. F. <hi>the Lye</hi> (but that was to <hi>G. F.</hi>) I cannot underſtand, that ſaying <hi>You</hi> to a ſingle Perſon, is a <hi>Lye,</hi> unleſs it be ſpoke to deceive: for I take a <hi>Lye</hi> to be a wilful <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:62826:4"/> for every <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntruth</hi> is not a <hi>Lye,</hi> becauſe one may ſpeak untrue, and yet not know but believes it is true; alſo <hi>Speech</hi> is only to ſignifie the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, and if the Party ſpoken to, plainly know the meaning of the Speaker, the end is anſwered, and that diſtinction rather proper for <hi>Schooles</hi> than <hi>Chriſtians:</hi> And this confident black-mouthed young man hath by thoſe few words marked as <hi>Lyers</hi> (and ſo for the <hi>Lake</hi>) hundreds of better Chriſtians than himſelf. But I know that with the Lord is more Mercy, alſo with the <hi>Chriſtian-Quaker</hi> more Charity. And I am ſatisfied <hi>J. P.</hi> is not the Young Man <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſaw, <hi>That was to mark thoſe that mourn for all the Abominations that be done in</hi> Jeruſalem: For I believe that among thoſe he hath marked as <hi>Lyers,</hi> there be many ſuch. I am ſorry his anger againſt <hi>T.C.</hi> ſhould ſo tranſport him to fall foul of ſo many Generations paſt, as alſo many now no ways concerned, nor privy to <hi>T.C</hi>'s Provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of him, that he is ſo offended at. For <hi>T. C.</hi> condemns none that are Conſcientious to God, although in different Practice, neither doth he queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on but they were, and are acceptable: But <hi>G.F.</hi> &amp;c. making Laws and Orders how People ſhould ſpeak and act, and yet pretend to Believe and Preach the Sufficiency of the <hi>New-Covenant,</hi> and dare not truſt them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, this I take to be a more denial of <hi>Chriſt being come in the Fleſh,</hi> than a peaceable Submiſſion to the Law, when nothing from God in the Heart is otherwiſe required. And I do believe that <hi>G. F.</hi> is not as <hi>Moſes,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Orders from; but HIM <hi>to whom all Judgment is committed.</hi> And who ever fixes Chriſt his Offices or Titles on <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. ſuch are Denyers of <hi>Chriſt being come in the Fleſh.</hi> And I am not againſt <hi>Goſpel-Order,</hi> but for it, as <hi>W. R.</hi> in the <hi>Third Part,</hi> and ſeveral other places in the <hi>Chriſtian-Quaker</hi> hath aſſerted.</p>
            <p>And for that <hi>J. P.</hi> is offended with <hi>T. C.</hi> in pag. 9. becauſe he ſaid, <hi>That may be required of one, which may not be required of another. T. C.</hi> did not ſay, <hi>It is ſo,</hi> but, <hi>may be,</hi> and if that be poſſible, as I am ſure it is, then what I af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, is truth, and I think the Parable of the <hi>Talents,</hi> &amp;c. makes that good, and as <hi>Iſ. Pennington</hi> ſaith, <hi>Though the Doings or Thoughts, or Words be Divers, yet if they proceed from the ſame Principle and Nature, there is a true <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity felt therein, where the Life alone is Judge.</hi> A ſmall grain of <hi>Charity,</hi> (much leſs than he hath of <hi>Enmity</hi>) would have ſhewed him how to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile ſuch <hi>Aſſertions</hi> to Truth: but to ſatisfie the honeſt hearted (and not to gratifie the <hi>Chief Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi>) <hi>T.C.</hi> doth ſay, That he believes many Chriſtians do out of Conſcience ſcruple <hi>Paying of Tithes,</hi> as believing it ſinful; and that it is required of ſuch, that they be faithful thereto; but he alſo believes that ſome honeſt People have not the ſame ſcruple or doubt, therefore it is not ſo required of them: and in this caſe it may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be ſaid, <hi>That is required of one, which may not be of another.</hi> For that <hi>J. P.</hi> queries of <hi>W. R.</hi> whether he will ſtand by <hi>T.C.</hi> thereby taking on
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62826:4"/> him to enquire for help for <hi>T. C.</hi> he need not, for <hi>T. C.</hi> never complained to him for, neither would he have any of his help, for he likes not his Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice ſo well: and <hi>T. C.</hi> fears not but he ſhall have ſufficient aſſiſtance as he is on Truths part, and otherways he doth not deſire any: but hopes never ſhall ſhelter under <hi>J. P</hi>'s Refuge, for I am ſure that muſt be ſwept away. And if not to pay <hi>Tithes</hi> be a fundamental or ſubſtantial Doctrine of <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion,</hi> (which is the higheſt it can be) hear what <hi>Iſaac Pennington</hi> in page 11. of <hi>Examination,</hi> ſpeaking of the Kingdom of God, faith, <hi>Another may want divers Doctrines concerning it, perhaps ſome of thoſe which men call FUNDAMENTAL,</hi> and yet be a Citizen of it, <hi>and in the Power,</hi> &amp;c. Alſo, ſee <hi>Edward Burrough</hi>'s Teſtimony, pag. 20. <hi>Notwithſtanding Difference in Judgment, in Caſes Subſtantial, yet they were to be in Love and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi> Whereby it appears from both their Writings, that they allowed dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in Practice and Judgment; <hi>in things eſteemed SUBSTANTIALS</hi> (and <hi>G. F</hi>'s Laws cannot be more.) And this was the Unity <hi>Iſaac Penning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> ſaith, pag. 88. <hi>Being thus kept, all will come into One Outwardly.</hi> I hope this raſh Young Man will not term his Father, and <hi>E. B.</hi> as he hath <hi>T. C. One that ſhuns the Croſs, and ſeeks Eaſe in the Fleſh,</hi> and ſay, <hi>They oppoſe Truth to Truth, and maketh the Spirit inconſiſtent with it ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſeeing <hi>Iſ. P</hi>'s words are ſuch undeniable Truths as cited by <hi>T. C</hi> which <hi>J. P.</hi> cannot deny, only ſaith, <hi>it is but in part his Fathers Senſe; T. C.</hi> never ſaid it was all, but in <hi>Preface</hi> referred to his Book. I hope <hi>J.P.</hi> will not make one Part contradict the other, for that would render himſelf guilty of what he falſly charges on <hi>W. R.</hi> and <hi>T. C.</hi> that they have abuſed and perverted his Fathers Writings, and thereby all thoſe black Characters that <hi>J. P.</hi> hath beſtowed on <hi>W. R.</hi> and <hi>T. C.</hi> juſtly belong to himſelf. And for that he hath been ſo extravagant (beyond his pretended Principle) to beſtow ſuch a <hi>Livery</hi> on <hi>T.C.</hi> and ſo abundantly belace it: I believe he never knew <hi>T. C.</hi> before the occaſion of theſe Teſtimonies; therefore ſeeing his knowledge was ſo little, neither hath he proved any great Crimes againſt him: I appeal to any <hi>Chriſtian Quaker,</hi> whether it be not a very unchriſtian and bold adventure of this black monthed Young Man to ſay, T.C. <hi>dayly doth deſpite to the Spirit of Grace, and that he opens a Gap to Libertiniſm.</hi> I deny all fleſhly Liberty and Eaſe, but the high Hedg, or Wall, <hi>viz. G. F</hi>'s <hi>Orders,</hi> &amp;c. muſt be deſtroyed, and that City layed waſt. (And every one know his dependence upon the Foundation Chriſt Jeſus, the Light) And what you have hewed and hammered, and made ſuch a noiſe with your Tools, they are not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the fitter for the Lords Houſe; for His Day is come, and coming on all your Fenced Cities and High Towers, and thoſe who like the poor <hi>Rekabites,</hi> cannot dwell in your Fenced Cities, nor drink of your Wine; theſe in all other Tribes as well as Yours, is the Lord gathering into the one Habitation,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62826:5"/> 
               <hi>the Light,</hi> although not into one <hi>Outward Form,</hi> yet of one Mind, and Heart, to do the <hi>Will of God,</hi> and ſerve each other; and here will be their Greatneſs, not in ſtriving to rule and command each other, and Preaching up Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to Elders, and thoſe to have Rule and Care of the Church, <hi>becauſe their Party have gotten the Dominion;</hi> but on the contrary, ſtrives who ſhall be Loweſt, moſt Meek, and Patient, and bear others Burthens, every one prefering his Brother before himſelf, and ſo Honour and Submiſſion is freely rendred, but not required: And as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid, <hi>Every one ſubject one to another, and all may Propheſy one by one, and the reſt Judge, and not one, or a few that will Propheſy and Judge to.</hi> And whereas the Apoſtle doth in ſome caſes allude to the Members of the Body to ſhew that ſeveral Offices or Gifts, differing, are uſeful, and that one ſhould not think much of another, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe not the ſame Member or Office. And although in a natural Body, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Member hath its fixt Office, it is not ſo in the Spiritual Body, but Place or Office may change; none, <hi>Eye</hi> or <hi>Hand</hi> for the whole Body conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fixed, but <hi>Eye,</hi> or <hi>Hand</hi> to day, may be Foot to morrow, and who ſeems contemptible to day, may to morrow be Honoured. And Chriſts Miniſters they have his Image of <hi>Meekneſs</hi> and <hi>Self-denyal,</hi> and what they deliver as from God, is commended to his <hi>Word of Grace</hi> in the Heart; for thoſe that Chriſt exalts will not exalt thcmſelves, but as Chriſt did when they would have made him King, then he hid himſelf, but when they came to take him to crucifie him; then he ſaid, <hi>Whom ſeek ye? I am he.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And notwithſtanded <hi>T.C.</hi> is by this <hi>J.P.</hi> &amp;c. rendred a <hi>Ranter,</hi> and <hi>Looſe Libertine,</hi> &amp;c. yet I will now give a brief Relation of the occaſion of <hi>T. C.</hi> his being concerned, alſo ſome hints of the Difference.</p>
            <p>Having heard in publick Meeting, alſo by Print and Writing, that <hi>I. S.</hi> and <hi>I.W.</hi> were Men of evil Practices and Principles, as by a Judgment given againſt them (by above 60 Perſons) wherein <hi>I.S.</hi> and <hi>I.W.</hi> were ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <hi>Obſtinate, Deſpiſers of Heavenly Dignities, promoting falſe pernicious Jealouſies, ſetting up a kind of a Standard of Separation from the Bleſſed Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of the Churches of Chriſt, bring Confuſion to the Churches.</hi> Theſe with more black Names and Terms, they ſay are <hi>in the Name, and by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Chriſt;</hi> alſo they refer to a Paper ſubſcribed by about 80 Friends in <hi>WeſtmorLand,</hi> wherein they ſay will be found the true Nature of Impoſition. Which is becauſe ſome Perſons that belonged not to their Meetings, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented them, and occaſioned Differences about <hi>G.F.</hi> his Laws; wherefore the Perſons concerned, deſired that they would not concern themſelves, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they had any Buſineſs or Meſſage from the Lord: wherein they made no abſolute excluſion of any: yet this is termed by <hi>G. F. Impoſition, worſe than any Court, Aſſize, or Seſſions,</hi> and yet theſe Meetings were for Buſineſs, <hi>viz,</hi> taking care of the Poor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as they were a Body, or People gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: And for Peace ſake, ſome abſented, and met apart, but propoſed that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62826:5"/> if they might enjoy their Freedom in Peace, and to act as in Conſcience per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, they would be content to meet with their other Brethren as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly; yet this is one chief Crime charged againſt them in your Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and one of <hi>G. F</hi>'s Party ſaid, <hi>They reſolve to give Battle to this Spirit in the Name of the Lord, where-ever they meet it:</hi> by which it appears they have proclaimed War, and therefore are termed <hi>G. F</hi>'s <hi>Men of War;</hi> and ſo far as I can find, the chief Cauſe is, that they (<hi>I. S.</hi> and <hi>I.W.</hi> &amp;c.) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Law of God and the Scriptures before <hi>G.F</hi>'s Laws: for all your Charges and Accuſations againſt them, you charge them not with Breach of the Law of God, or the Nation, or Perſonal Wrongs, as Men, but Diſſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factions about your Forms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the Conſideration of the <hi>Innocency</hi> of <hi>I.S.</hi> and <hi>I.W.</hi> and the <hi>Severe</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt Sentence</hi> againſt them, and other publick defaming them, occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned ſome to appear in their Vindication, and indeed it concerns them, and all Friends as Men, as well as Chriſtians: for if <hi>G. F.</hi> or any one Man, or Company, terming themſelves the <hi>Body,</hi> or <hi>Church</hi> (and uſurping Authority) have Power to impoſe Laws on others, and contrary to their Conſciences, they muſt thereto conform, or are <hi>Apoſtates</hi> and <hi>Inſidels:</hi> this makes void the <hi>New-Covenent,</hi> or <hi>Law</hi> in the Heart, and is ſo unlike, nay, contraay to <hi>True Chriſtianity,</hi> that I am aſtoniſhed thereat; Chriſt ſaid, <hi>What ever you would others ſhould do unto you, that do unto them,</hi> &amp;c. And I am well ſatisfied theſe Perſons themſelves would not he ſo impoſed on. And becauſe <hi>I.W.</hi> ſaid, <hi>That they ought to uſe no Force but the Word of Life to ſtir up People, and that they would not have People over driven.</hi> And <hi>I.S.</hi> ſaid, <hi>He believed one was an honeſt Friend, and yet had not a Teſtimony againſt Tithes.</hi> Theſe and ſuch like <hi>Chriſtian Expreſſions</hi> are accounted ſuch black Sins, that they be made Heads of Articles againſt them: And if ſuch Proceedings be not like <hi>Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> and <hi>Impoſition,</hi> I know not What is. I mean not, that they would intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the <hi>Pope of Rome</hi> to have Power here in <hi>England,</hi> but themſelves, <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. would have Power, and do aſſume and maintain, <hi>That they have Power and Wiſdom from God to determin the Affairs of the Church;</hi> and do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate, and come little ſhort of <hi>Rome,</hi> according to their Power; but many do bleſs God, that ſome of them have no Power to mulct, or corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>really puniſh, but they ſay they have Power in Heaven, a great deal, and do not only lay a ſmall Fine for not Conforming, but ſeize the whole Eſtate, and baniſh thence effectually to their utmoſt: and for Matters of leſs coucernment than eating Fleſh or Herbs, or obſerving a Day, or not; for the Outward Life may in great meaſure depend on ſome of theſe ſometimes. But <hi>G.F.</hi> his Laws about <hi>Womens Meetings,</hi> and <hi>Form of Marriages</hi> be termed from the <hi>Oracles of Divine; Breath, Heavenly Dignities, Chriſts Government,</hi> and the conforming to them, <hi>Proſperity of Sion, Peace of Jeruſalem,</hi> and almoſt all
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62826:6"/> high Titles in Scripture, and they ſtamp the Inventions of <hi>G. F.</hi> and his Party with the Authority of the Spirit of God, if but about Time or Place of Meeting; which if ſcrupled for ſome reaſons of Inconveniences of Time or Place, or out of Conſcience to avoid <hi>Superſtition in Forms;</hi> for ſuch ſmall Matters have ſome been rendred, <hi>Diſturbers of the Churches Peace:</hi> as if all Good and Hope of Salvation ſtood only in them: nay, in their <hi>Bull</hi> of 66. againſt <hi>I.S.</hi> and <hi>I.W.</hi> after all the black Characters given them, they do ſay, <hi>By the Power and Spirit of God— they warn all to beware of them,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and to warn them to go home, and be reconciled to their Brethren,</hi> &amp;c. (<hi>i.e.</hi>) <hi>Submit to</hi> G.F. and ſay, <hi>therein will ye acquit your ſelves in Gods Sight.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it appears what Value and Force they eſteem their Orders, that the bare obſerving them <hi>can abſolve:</hi> a cheap way to Heaven, if you can believe all theſe Men ſay, and that they be the only <hi>Diſpenſers of the Goſpel:</hi> but as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious and careful as theſe new Spiritual Lords would make the honeſt hearted believe they are, for the Glory of God and Proſperity of Truth; it appears by their ſevere Judgment, and heatheniſing. <hi>I.S.</hi> and <hi>I. W.</hi> &amp;c. and their condemning <hi>I. A.</hi> becauſe out of Conscience they cannot conform to <hi>G. F</hi>'s Laws, and their excuſing <hi>S. E.</hi> who ſpeak <hi>Lyes</hi> in the Name of the Lord; alſo the high Praiſes given the <hi>Barbadoes Church,</hi> notwithſtanding their ſo erroneous Judgment in purſuance of <hi>G. F</hi>'s Laws, as in <hi>Babel-Buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> it more fully appears, that their Care is for <hi>G. F</hi>'s Laws, more than the Laws of God.</p>
            <p>And the conſideration of the Inconſiſtency of the <hi>Principles of Truth,</hi> with their <hi>Church-Government,</hi> is cauſe of aſtoniſhment to many; remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring that under pretences of every one walking as they were by the Light in their Conſciences perſwaded, they gathered many honeſt People out of all Societies; and now term <hi>Outward Orders</hi> (about needleſs Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies) ordered by <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Chriſts Government,</hi> and no being Members of Chriſts Church, without ſo owning them, and yet their own <hi>Liberty,</hi> but at pleaſure of others: conſidering all Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, I think ſcarce any <hi>Impoſers</hi> now extant, if they be not: and the conſideration of what ill Conſequence it may prove to the After-Ages, if <hi>G.F.</hi> and his Party but gain that Point of Power, <hi>viz. To give Laws to others,</hi> and that it is their Duty to be conformable thereto, although contrary to their Conſciences; Or that any one of <hi>G. F</hi>'s. Party pretending them ſeyes Publick Labourers or Miniſters, muſt not be denyed Inſpection into others Affairs, for fear of being accounted <hi>Impoſers,</hi> worſe than any <hi>Court, Aſſize,</hi> or <hi>Seſſions,</hi> as <hi>G. F.</hi> did the <hi>Weſtmorland</hi> Friends: I ſay, the Apprehenſion of the ill Effects of theſe Principles and Practices: If ſome others ſhould but have the Confidence to give ſuch Names, and Dignities (as <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. have done) to their Laws and Ceremonies now in uſe, and ſome of them in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as inoffenſive as <hi>G. F</hi>'s, only too much ſtreſs laid on them. I dread
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62826:6"/> to think the ill Conſequences thereof: it was truly ſaid, <hi>That Popery, leaſt ſuſpected, will do us moſt harm.</hi> For when <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> pretended to the <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Biſhoprick, Rome</hi> then ſeemed as much againſt what the now is, as ſome now do, for all they may, now ſay, <hi>Am I a Dog</hi> (as one once did) and yet did that he then ſeemed ſo to abhor: and of all People in <hi>England,</hi> miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Slaves be we poor <hi>Quakers,</hi> better and ſafer to ſubmit to a <hi>Church</hi> that have their Atticles fixed, or the Scripture for their Rule, for thereby we may know what may be required, their Power being limited; but <hi>G. F's</hi> &amp;c. not. For they have a <hi>High Tower,</hi> where they think themſelves ſo ſafe, that none can reach them, and that is their pretence to <hi>their Church-Power,</hi> which others pretend to as well as they; therefore it was truly ſaid in <hi>Adr. to Prot. Eithor convince my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, or ſhew me a Miracle;</hi> but that failed; for that Deceiver <hi>S.E.</hi> would have forged one on I.S. (when in like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood not to live long) belying the Lord, and ſaying, <hi>That year he ſhould dye;</hi> but hath ſince confeſſed it was falſe. A cheap way of buying Pardons, and great Incouragement for other his Fellow Servants to <hi>G. F.</hi> to do the ſame; who make ſuch a noiſe of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſubjected Spirits</hi> to the <hi>Yoke of Chriſt,</hi> as if there were no <hi>Yoke of Chriſt,</hi> but <hi>G. F.</hi>'s Orders. Is not Pure Religion, now the ſame as ever? Is the Lord changed, or the Force of Faith abated? for by that the <hi>Elders</hi> obtained a good Report; and that <hi>Sure Word</hi> that <hi>Peter</hi> directed to, was more ſure than the Voice that was heard in the <hi>Mount;</hi> and is now as Sure and Powerful as ever; and if ſurer to that Church when <hi>Peter</hi> wrote to them, then that formerly ſpoke to Chriſt in the Mount, although <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf a Witneſs of it: then more ſure and ſafe than <hi>G. F</hi>'s, &amp;c. For as his great Champion and Servant <hi>S.E.</hi> was miſtaken, ſo may he, and better to undergo their Falſe Judgment, than that of God in the Conſcience, although they may ſay, <hi>You deſpiſe Dignities, and diſturb the Churches, and be Apoſtates,</hi> &amp;c. Remember it was <hi>Pharaoh</hi> of old that ſaid to the <hi>Children of Iſrael, Ye are idle;</hi> and the Enemies to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> time ſaid, when they went to repair the Breaches, <hi>They would Rebel, and damage the Kings Tribute,</hi> and the <hi>Jews</hi> cryed out of the Apoſtles, <hi>That if they were let alone, the</hi> Romans <hi>would come and take Place and Nation,</hi> as <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. faith, <hi>Make us a Deriſion to the Heathen, and lay waſt Gods Heritage.</hi> It is the Old Lording Spirit that hath followed, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred all Forms that hath entered <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. who would (<hi>Pharaoh like</hi>) keep in Bondage, therefore ſay, <hi>Ye are Idle, and weary of the Croſs, and would go back into</hi> Egypt: but I know not what looks more like, <hi>Egypt,</hi> than being tasked by <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. and be in Bondage to them who muſt give, or rather command what, and how much we muſt do, to have our Work and Task ſet by them, that is <hi>AEgypt,</hi> and contrary to the Apoſtle, who when deſired to concern himſelf, by complaint about the neglect of ſome Widdows, he ſaid, <hi>Chooſe ye out faithful Men, ſhall we leave the Work of the Lord to ſerve Tables?</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:62826:7"/> But <hi>G.F</hi>'s Party contrary to this Example, they will call it <hi>Impoſition</hi> and(<hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependency</hi>) worſe than <hi>Court, Aſſize,</hi> or <hi>Seſſions,</hi> if you will not let them med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with your Buſineſs, when unconcerned, altho they have liberty to deliver any thing they have from God. Oh poor ſlaves, the under Members of your Body. For I would know the Security that any thing one hath, is their own; if but <hi>G.E.</hi> or <hi>S. E.</hi> pretend ſomething on their Spirits, which <hi>C.T.</hi> may term <hi>From the Oracle of Divine Breath:</hi> you muſt be at Unity (that is, give up) or elſe erred from your Meaſures. The Dangerouſneſs of theſe Doctrines, and their ſuch early Proceedings thereon, cauſes ſome to think no pains ill ſpent to <hi>Detect</hi> and <hi>Lay Naked</hi> ſuch Men and Principles, that it may be known that <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. are not the beſt among the <hi>Quakers,</hi> nor the beſt of Gods Servants, as <hi>C. T.</hi> &amp;c. have falſly affirmed; For there be thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands among them abhor ſuch things, (although the ruling Party term them <hi>Apoſtates,</hi> &amp;c.) who deſire no more Liberty than they are willing to allow to others differing from them, and deſire, as Chriſt ſaid, <hi>To do as they would be done by.</hi> But theſe Ruling <hi>Foxonians</hi> do exceed the Church of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> who were ſaid <hi>To have a Name to live,</hi> but theſe few have taken to themſelves almoſt all the Living Names and High Titles that can be found in Scripture, but the Life would do them more goodl; more Life, and fewer Titles; read what was ſaid to <hi>Laodicea, Thou ſayeſt thou art Rich, and increaſed with Goods, but kneweſt not that thou wert Blind and Naked.</hi> Names of Living, and ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they be rich, are not ſuch good Signs, proud boaſting ſwelling words be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeak not ſo much <hi>Chriſts Life,</hi> as <hi>Iſ. P.</hi> ſays to <hi>New-England; They have long had a Form, and it may be, have eaten up the Power, and they may not be ſo Savoury now in their Eaſe, and Authority, as under their Trouble and Perſecutions, and God may in kindneſs to them ſend among them a Fooliſh People to ſtir them up — now their coming is not to ſcatter corrupt Opinions, but by the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Truth to ſcatter that which ſcattereth from the Lord; nor is it to draw to their way, but to the Lord, and the Living Way which they are exhorted to try before they receive.</hi> So that all who Endeavour to promote Forms more than Peace and Charity, which are the very Life of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> gives juſt Cauſe to ſuſpect the Lord doth not ſend them: and this as certainly belongs to <hi>G.F:</hi> his Party (who aſſume to themſelves the Rule and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment) as it did to <hi>New-England,</hi> for you are doing the ſame Work as they did; (I do not mean hanging, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) but cry out as they did, <hi>Diſturb the Church, preach Heretical Opinions, deny Chriſts Goſpel and Miniſters, and Chriſts Ordinances:</hi> and what for? but not Preaching up, or not conforming to ſome New Laws of theſe New Spiritual Lords, <hi>viz. G. F.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Alſo in a <hi>Poſtſcript</hi> to <hi>S. C</hi>'s <hi>Babyloniſh Oppoſer,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>J. P.</hi> ſaith, that <hi>T.C.</hi> hath curtailed a Teſtimony of his Dear Fathers: but if any deſerve to be termed <hi>Curtailers,</hi> or <hi>Perverters,</hi> then it belongs to the Writer and Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of the <hi>Accuſer,</hi> &amp;c. who cite Part of the Title to the <hi>Third Part of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62826:7"/> Chriſtian Quaker,</hi> but they leave out in the middle of the Sentence ſome of the Principle words, <hi>viz. Who alone is Lord of the Conſcience;</hi> and ſome O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and <hi>W. R</hi>'s next words be, <hi>For the better illuſtration of our Meaning, an Anſwer to a Part of a Book of</hi> R. B. <hi>is cited.</hi> By which words it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, that in Juſtice no Concluſion ought to be made from that Title, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſulting that Anſwer referred to: but yet they do in the <hi>Accuſer,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, a Sheet put out in the Name of <hi>T. L.</hi> Alſo <hi>J. P</hi>'s Complaint, page 5. ſay of <hi>W.R's. The whole Drift of that Part is to tye up all to an Inward Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of Chriſt, excluſive of any Outward Government,</hi> &amp;c. Whereby it is evident they would perſwade Friends that <hi>W. R.</hi> &amp;c. is againſt Order, &amp;c. and yet they do cite in the <hi>Accuſer,</hi> by way of Contradiction to <hi>W.R.</hi> from that Anſwer in 23d.pag. of the <hi>Third Part,</hi> that <hi>W. R.</hi> ſayeth, <hi>Not that I would be underſtood that it is not neceſſary to be in the Exerciſe of Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Order, with reſpect of Goſpel, Diſcipline, and from page 83. of the</hi> Third Part, <hi>My Soul ſhould rejoyce to ſee that Day, wherein we might all be ſo led by the Appearance of Chriſts Spirit in us, that Oneneſs might thereby be witneſſed among all the Families of Gods People.</hi> Alſo 38. and 43. pages of the <hi>Firſt Part,</hi> and 47. of the <hi>Second,</hi> and 33.64. and 65. of the <hi>Third.</hi> All theſe be by themſelves cited out of <hi>C. Q.</hi> which do plainly manifeſt <hi>W. R.</hi> is not againſt <hi>Order,</hi> and <hi>Oneneſs,</hi> nor <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> as they falſly charge him, but they <hi>Falſe Accuſers</hi> (ſo proved by their own Citations) and <hi>Curtailers,</hi> as in the 5th. page of the <hi>Accuſer,</hi> &amp;c. They cite a Place from page 21. of the <hi>Firſt Part</hi> of the <hi>C. Q. W. R.</hi> ſays <hi>This Sensence,<note place="margin">THeſe Words in diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Letters, were left out in their Citation.</note> as Heirs of the Goſpel of Life &amp; Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on take your Poſſeſſons <hi>hath been</hi> of late Years frequently expreſt <hi>by G. F. when ſpeaking to Friends,</hi> by way of Incouragement to continue Men and Womens Meetings <hi>diſtinct from the Publick Meeting for VVorſhip,</hi> by which it is much doubted that ſome Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant People have <hi>concluded that the</hi> frequenting ſuch Meetings, is an Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that they are Heirs of Life and Salvation.</hi> Where they leave out <hi>G.F.</hi> his Name, and other material words, &amp;c. and ſay <hi>W. R.</hi> reflects on he knows not who, when he names <hi>G. F.</hi> and as they quote his words, they ſeem a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Reflection on Meetings for Worſhip, when <hi>W. R.</hi> ſays <hi>diſtinct from them,</hi> and they have left out and added words in many Places to the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Perverſion of the Senſe, and according to their own Meaſures, are <hi>Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailers</hi> and <hi>Perverters,</hi> and have ſo far excelled <hi>T. Hicks</hi> and <hi>I. Ives,</hi> that if any People (pretending to <hi>Chriſts Church,</hi> &amp;c.) may be ſaid to have attained to the perfection of that they themſelves call <hi>Forgery, Perverting, and Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailing:</hi> they, <hi>viz.</hi> G.F's <hi>Chief Men of War,</hi> have, as appears in their <hi>Accuſer,</hi> alſo their <hi>Hypocriſy Detected,</hi> put out in the Name of that poor Aged Man <hi>T. L.</hi> of 81 Years, and touſe their own Expreſſions, who would have thought they ſhould have the Face to accuſe others for that they are ſo groſly guilty of, and have the confidence to ſay that <hi>T. C. hath the face to bring up the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62826:8"/> Names of</hi> Iſ. P. <hi>and</hi> E. B. <hi>again with the ſame tendency, to render their Senſe different from their Brethrens preſent Practice, is no leſs than a manifeſt Perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. I my ſelf know that my Father hath delivered to the contrary, and never ſaw, nor heard any thing contradictory thereto come from him.</hi> Wherefore I ſhall mention ſome more of their <hi>preſent Senſe or Judgment,</hi> alſo <hi>Iſ. P. Teſtimonys,</hi> and leave their Inconſiſtency to the Judgment of the <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Theſe under, are their <hi>Preſent Judgment</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Theſe following are <hi>Iſ. P's</hi> &amp; <hi>E.B's Judgment formerly.</hi> Iſ. P. EXAM. 10.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Pag. 2. Epiſtle Brief Examination.</hi> Speaking of the <hi>Church,</hi> ſay, <hi>Her Members are of one Mind in Church-Matters.</hi> And P. 4. <hi>no fear of want of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, where all are left with the One Spirit of Truth, they muſt be of one Mind, they cannot be otherwiſe.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>The true Tryal of Spirits is not by an Aſſent to Doctrines, which a <hi>Hypocrite</hi> may aſſent to. 11. A man may want ſome of thoſe Doctrines Men call FUNDAMENTALS, and yet be a Citizen of it (<hi>i. e.</hi> Heaven.) <hi>E. B.</hi> notwithſtanding difference in Judgment in Caſes Subſtantial yet they were to walk together in Love and Unity.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>And I deſire Friends to conſider theſe Sayings of <hi>Iſ. P.</hi> and <hi>E. B.</hi> now Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and many more, and compare with what is alſo Cited againſt them, and their Severe Perſecution of <hi>I.S. I.W. I.A.</hi> and others, for not Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to <hi>G. F</hi>'s Laws, but for ſhewing Charity to ſome honeſt Men that dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered from them in ſome things. And <hi>I. S.</hi> and <hi>I. W. ſaid, They would not have People over driven.</hi> And this <hi>Chriſtian Charity</hi> which <hi>Iſ. P</hi>'s and <hi>E. B</hi>'s an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Teſtimonies accord with, (and ſo ought all in Truth) <hi>G. F</hi>'s Party are ſo Apoſtatiſed from, (rendring them ſuch Evil Facts) that they make them Heads of Articles; nay, for differing about Manner or Form of Marriages, ſhall condemn out of Unity, which is out of the <hi>Church of Christ,</hi> with them, as by their Principle afore Cited, <hi>muſt be all of one Mind, cannot be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe:</hi> but the Teſtimonies cited of <hi>I. P</hi>'s and <hi>E. B.</hi>'s ſay contrary.</p>
            <p>And therefore, who cannot adore <hi>G. F.</hi> and his Laws, as <hi>C. T.</hi> &amp;c. have done, <hi>From the Oracle of Divine Breath,</hi> and <hi>S. E. The great and good Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer of Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> and if not of one Mind with them, and will not give up to his <hi>Womens Meetings,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Then Rebels againſt the Lord, and Curſed from God from all Eternity to all Eternity,</hi> as ſome of <hi>G. F</hi>'s Men of War have ſaid, becauſe ſome will not bow to <hi>G. F</hi>'s Will: And he himſelf hath ſaid, thoſe that be of <hi>I. S</hi>'s Party, <hi>be of the Devils Party,</hi> then out of the Truth, and not ſafe to be left to their Freedom, or as <hi>G.F.</hi> ſays, to the <hi>Barbadoes Church, Thoſe that have not <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity with Mens and Womens Meetings, are erred from their Meaſures, but the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Spirit hath <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity with the leaſt Meaſure.</hi> So
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62826:8"/> that they that are not of one Mind with them, have not the leaſt Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, for if they had, they ſhould have Unity with them. Which Doctrine is alſo confirmed, in their <hi>Brief Examination,</hi> pag. 2. and 3. <hi>If thou are ſuch an one that can do nothing againſt the Truth, but for the Truth, then mayeſt thou ſafely be left to thy Freedom in the things of God:</hi> which words do imply, that it is not for others to expect it, or have right to it, as confirmed a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel farther, where having ſpoke of ſome good things, then ſay, <hi>That if thou plead thy Freedom againſt ſuch things,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>thy Freedom is nought, and out of Truth.</hi> Now with thoſe, and many more ſuch good Names, and Rich Attire, do they dreſs <hi>G. F</hi>'s Laws with: and who cannot, as <hi>C. T.</hi> and <hi>S. E.</hi> adore him, and them, as they have, then <hi>Your Freedom's nought, and out of Truth,</hi> and by the Conſequence of the above cited Doctrine, It is not fit for you to be left to your Freedom in the things of God, unleſs you be arrived to that heigth of <hi>Hypocritical</hi> and <hi>Phariſaical Righteouſneſs</hi> as <hi>C.T.</hi> &amp;c. (who in his Epiſtle of <hi>Caution</hi> is of the ſame mind with <hi>Exam.</hi>) <hi>He would have it Believed they cannot appoint any thing againſt, but for the Truth,</hi> whereby it is manifeſt that their Charity <hi>for Freedom in the Things of God,</hi> (i. e. Liberty of Conſcience) extends to ſuch as can own <hi>G. F.</hi> for the beſt of Gods Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and his Laws <hi>from the Oracle of Divine Breath;</hi> but thoſe who cannot ſo believe, their Freedom is nought, and they out of Truth, although never ſo Conſcientious to God otherwiſe. But <hi>Ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. to Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t.</hi> p. 104, ſaith. <hi>Faith in that day was an intire Reſignation and Dependence on God, and not a Subſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Verbal Propoſitions and Articles, although never ſo true.</hi> P. 105 <hi>Thou ſhall love the Lord thy God with all thy Heart, and thy Neighbour as thy ſelf; is the perfection Chriſtian Religion, — and certain Token of a Diſciple.</hi> Theſe Qualifications may be, and yet not of one Mind in ſome Forms; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are all the Members of Chriſts Church arrived to that State (or not to that height of Preſumption) as <hi>G. T.</hi> &amp;c. but on the contrary; may through unwatchfulneſs and weakneſs do ſome things diſpleaſing to God: therefore not for, but againſt the Truth, yet ought to be left to their Freedom in the Things of God. And that Poſition, <hi>That them which be left with the one Spirit of Truth, muſt be of one Mind, cannot be otherwiſe;</hi> I take to be falſe, For <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> differed, and were not of one Mind in ſome things, yet I hope you will not deny them to be Members of Chriſts Church, and to be left to their Freedom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſeeing you have ſo much Chriſtian Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for Moral Men to admit they may be Chriſtians. It is ſaid, p. 7. of <hi>Brief Exam.</hi> 
               <q>The difference between <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifies the weakneſs of <hi>Peter,</hi> and —Juſtifies <hi>Pauls</hi> Reproof of his too great Complyance with the <hi>Jews.</hi>
               </q> — Which makes againſt Liberty of various Practices in the 'Church. But I take him to miſtake, for <hi>Peter</hi> not only complyed to the <hi>Jews</hi> himſelf, but he Would conſtrain the <hi>Gentils</hi> to do like the <hi>Jews.</hi> Gal 2. v. 14.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62826:9"/> Therefore <hi>Paul</hi> withſtood him, and it was not the believing, or practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing one or'tother, for he ſaid Circumciſion or Uncircumciſion avail not; alſo he cauſed <hi>Timothy</hi> to be Circumciſed, but it was the Preaching of Forms or Ceremonies of neceſſity to Salvation, that he terms <hi>Compelling, Act. 15. Certain Men taught the Gentiles, that except they were Circumciſed, and kept the Law of</hi> Moſes, <hi>they could not be Saved.</hi> This <hi>Paul</hi> withſtood. Alſo it is ſaid, <hi>Br. Exam.</hi> page 7. <hi>That Paſſage about Eating hath nothing in it for which it is alledged, for it related not to Church Order or Communion:</hi> But I think it did, for in the Qu. before, it is ſaid, <hi>The Perſons differing, were</hi> Peter <hi>and</hi> Paul, <hi>and</hi> Peter <hi>eat with the</hi> Gentils, <hi>as</hi> Gal. 2.12. alſo 1. Cor. 8.10. <hi>If any ſee thee which haſt Knowledge, ſit at Table in the Idols Temple, ſhall not the Conſcience of him that is weak be imboldned to eat thoſe things ſacrificed to Idols.</hi> Alſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. The Apoſtle ſpeaks of obſerving Days to the Lord, as well as eating, and about offending one another, which could not ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be in what any eats in private, as his Nouriſhment, but related to ſome Differences about Meats, which ſome would have oblieged the <hi>Believing Gentiles</hi> to obſerve the <hi>Jews</hi> Ceremonies therein, on account of Salvation, as in <hi>Act.</hi> 15. which <hi>Paul</hi> was againſt, and they had Diſputes about. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. <hi>Him that is weak receive not to doubtful Diſputations:</hi> and in the next words the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>One believeth he may eat all things, another that is weakeateth Herbs:</hi> and in <hi>Verſ. 5. Let Every Man be fully perſwaded in his own Mind,</hi> and <hi>Verſ. 12. Every one ſhall give account of himſelf to God; let us not therefore judge one another.</hi> Theſe Scriptures and Citations clearly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt that Chriſtians ought to be left <hi>to their Freedom,</hi> (i. e. <hi>Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi>) although not ſo ſtrong, or at leaſt, not ſo confident as <hi>C. T.</hi> &amp;c. But if it be, as ſaid in page 7. <hi>Br. Exam.</hi> It related only to <hi>what they would Eat, as private Perſons in reſpect to Appetite:</hi> although they had therein Power, yet the Apoſtle adviſes to the conſideration of others: as <hi>Rom. 14.14. I know and am perſwaded that there is nothing unclean of it ſelf.</hi> Yet in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13. <hi>If Meat offend my Brother, I will eat no Fleſh while the World ſtandeth.</hi> Now if <hi>Paul</hi> would thus deny himſelf in condeſcenſion to a weak Brother, ſurely he was far from compelling him to be of his Mind, or ſaying, <hi>They cannot be otherwiſe.</hi> Therefore if that Inſtance about Meats related only to private Freedoms, that makes much more againſt a neceſſity of all being of one Mind, but rather according to <hi>Iſ. Ps</hi> &amp;c. Teſtimonies for leaving them to their Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, walking in Love and Unity in <hi>Diverſity of Practices.</hi> Wherefore that aſtoniſhing Affirmation of <hi>I. P.</hi> That he <hi>never ſaw nor heard any thing contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory to the preſent Senſe and Practice of Friends</hi> (i. e. G. F. and his Party) <hi>from his Father;</hi> ſeemed to me ſo remote from Truth, that I wonder <hi>(to uſe their own words)</hi> they have the <hi>Face</hi> to aſſert it. I recommend you all to the word of Gods Grace nigh in your Hearts, which is able to give you an Inheritance among the Sanctified Ones, which neither <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming to his Orders can do.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho. Criſp.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
